All right, friends, so next we move on and talk about conditions and conditions is what you can write in.
If block, you can write them in a search case, you can write those in loops, right?
So they're an important part of any programming language, not just in Java.
And starting with the if and then obviously we're going to use these operators, the comparison operators,
the logical operators within these conditions.
But first, as I said, you need to understand how conditions work.
So I'm just going to create a new one in the Java class and just going to call it conditional logic.
Right.
And we're just going to again have the main method.
Let's maximize this as always.
And now what is the syntax of writing a if condition in Java?
It just goes like this.
As you say, if condition and then a block, that's it.
Else is optional, obviously.
So that is additional.
If you want a condition, if that is not true, something else should happen.
That is where you put in the else block like this.
And the rule is that if can exist on it soon, but else cannot.
And if there is an if else, if should immediately be followed by an else block, right?
And these color braces, they're optional, if you just have one statement in your if or an else, they become optional.
But if you're multiple links, then you have to put them inside color braces.
So within this condition, if I just keep it, if I just keep it simple, if I just say a stout, I'll say again,
enter your ID and you'll just say int ID to new scanner green right here on this line system dot in dot next to it.
This is the succinct way of using scanner, but if you just have to use it once, if you have to use it multiple lines in your program, then I'll just suggest to declare it the earlier way with the variable and then get it in the next end to the next string or.
Or the next line sorry to different lines, but for now it takes a number and then I want to compare it, for example, whether this is an even or an odd number center program, simple logic, I'll say if I D, and you know the logic is that is if I D divided or divided by two, it's equal to equal to zero.
All right, any number that you would enter right if the division is zero, I'll just put in the sound I'll say.
You entered and even.
And then I could have said something like this if I D.
Why did by two is not equal to zero right means this is an or number I'll say you entered an or.
All right, simple simple program this and this is where I've used this comparison operator that operator that is division right here so not sorry not this one this is the arithmetic operator, but this is the equal to equal to assignment operator right.
And the resulting value should be a Boolean that's what it is and I'll just run this up and let's say entry ready I'll say to 30.
You entered an odd number because my logic is wrong I need to use the modules.
Right, because we need to check the remainder right not the quotient so I'll just run this and I'll say to 30 you entered an even number I'll say 475 you enter an odd number just works for any number that you enter so this is the is equal to.
And the not equal to two comparison operators that I used, but similarly you can use the less than greater than less than equal to greater than equal to again, not just because you have to based on a requirement there is right.
And I'll just talk about the variation it just works like in other languages these operators, but there is a small but significant variation here with how these operators work in Java.
But if you would have something done something like this mistakenly or incidentally you just put an instead of and by the way let's keep it like this for now now see I just have one line within the if so what I can do is I could have removed the call.
Let's take the course code less verbose see because they just have one lines and I told you the same semi columns there become optional they don't are man they don't become mandatory so I can even further make it succeed, I do I need a condition because see if there's an even number that said.
The other condition would not work, but if this condition is false then this should work so that means it's a classic case to use an else block.
And again because there's just one line so I don't have to use a curly braces that's on you right so if this is true this doesn't execute this is false this doesn't execute and this executes and still should give you the same results I'll say one oh one you've entered an on number.
That's it now mistakenly if you do something like this now see in a language like see your C++ this would have worked, why because it said ID modules to equal to zero what is this two is it does the modulus and then assigns zero to the.
As a resulting value of this expression to if but there it works because anything that is a zero is also considered a false in C or C++ but Java said this would be.
A redundancy right, which would confuse developers so a false is a false a true is a true in Java right and it says that if gets zero right what does that mean if should just get the conditions resulting value of this expression should just be a Boolean and a Boolean is a true or a false that's why it's in error it says, required type Boolean I was expecting a Boolean but I did get something else right that's why it doesn't work here.
So but remember that syntax is not the problem this kind of a syntax works in a different situation the problem is what is the conditions resulting value and if that is not a Boolean it's going to be an error in Java right so.
So that's why it's an error right but in C++ works but I told you in a different case this would have worked like for example let me say I have a Boolean variable I'll just call it flag and let me put what's there see now if I have to check it somewhere I say if flag and you put in the value equal to equal to true let's say I want to print sound.
Well, okay, so this works but mistakenly me miss or incidentally you just remove this and you said equal to and this still works not an error just a warning because now what is happening is you saying if flag flag is false you're assigning through it so true is a sign to flag and then what does if get if flag flag is Boolean it gets a Boolean it just works and even and that's why I told you the syntax was never a problem it is what if should get in now even if you remove this you.
If you remove this you can even use it like the same if flag.
So that means because now if you're saying if flag flag is Boolean this is acceptable but if it is anything other than a Boolean it would be an error in Java but even this works it says if flag if it is true then please print this if not do not print anything because I'm not put in a different if I'm not put in a else right so but that is how it works right.
so I say works right so basically works doesn't mean that this should execute because it's a false this block would not be executed but I'm just telling you this is the variation in the syntax what works here what doesn't what is different with other programming languages.